Guide to the Faneuil Weisse Collection of Student Notebooks MC.227
New York University Archives
Faneuil Weisse Collection of Student Notebooks
1881-1912
New York University Archives
Weisse, Faneuil D. (Faneuil Dunkin), 1842-1915
MC.227
2 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes
The Faneuil Weisse Collection of Student Notebooks are a collection of notebooks written by students of Dr. Weisse covering the oral surgery clinics he conducted at New York College of Dentistry. Dr. Weisse was a founding faculty member of NYCD in 1865 and acted as Dean from 1897-1912. The notebooks cover his oral surgery clinics from 1881-1912, with some gaps and some overlaps. This collection will be of great value to anyone interested in the history of dentistry, oral surgery and medicine in general. The case studies provide a look at some interesting cases and are a primary source demonstrating what best practices were considered to be in the field at the turn of the century.
Arrangement
No discernable arrangement existed prior to creation of finding aid in September 2013. Current arrangement is chronological.
Related Materials
Records of the New York University College of Dentistry (RG 25), Morris Mestel Collection on Saint Apollonia (MC 177), I. Franklin Miller Papers (MC 180)
Access
Materials are open. Some materials in this collection are extremely fragile and require preservation treatment before being served to researchers.
Scope and Contents
The Faneuil Weisse Collection of Student Notebooks consist of twenty-two notebooks containing notes on oral surgery clinics led by Faneuil Weisse between 1881 and 1912. The clinic notebooks are variously titled as Reports, Records, or Notes, but are essentially all versions of the same "Annual Record of Oral Surgery Clinics" containing details of case studies presented by Professor Weisse at the New York College of Dentistry. Two of them have very peculiar titles; "Styposulphide of Soda" and Inshallah Malaish ( followed by text indicating that this is Arabic for God willing - who knows!) but contain the same type of clinical notes as the other volumes. The notebooks were written by different student authors over the years. Some of the reports are in manuscript form and others from later dates are typed or printed. The topics covered in the clinics range from simple cleft palates to more unusual incidents, like amputating a patient's finger and fusing it to their face in order to create a new nose.
Biographical / Historical
The New York College of Dentistry was founded in 1865 with only 31 students and 10 faculty members. One of the founders and first faculty members was Faneuil D. Weisse, an MD oral surgeon. Weisse stayed on as a faculty member for many years and served as Dean of the College from 1897 - 1912. Weisse passed away in 1915. The school became part of New York University in 1925 and was known as New York University College of Dentistry from then on.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
NYU College of Dentistry's Waldman Library transfered their archival collections to the University Archives in August 2003. The accession record associated with this collections is 03-006.
Mattiau, Harry; Berger, Adolph; Heindsmann, F., Jr.; Moser, Oscar L.; Hubbell, Charles Gregory; Haffenden, C. Radcliffe; Howe, Clarence; New York University. College of Dentistry
- Series I, 1881-1912
  - 1881-82 - "Professor Weisse's Cliniques at the NY College of Dentistry" by Oscar L. Moser (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1883-85 - "Notes of Oral Cliniques" by a Senior (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1884-85 - "Clinics by Prof. F. Weisse" by F. Heindsmann Jr. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1886-87 - Clinical Record NYCD (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1888-89 - NYCD Report of Clinics (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1889-90 - Notes on Oral Surgery Clinic - NYCD (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1892 - NYCD Clinic Notes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1892-93 - NYCD Clinic Notes (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1893-94 - NYCD - Notes on Professor Weisse's Clinic" by C. Radcliffe Haffenden (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1897-98 - Report of Oral History Clinics (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1898-99 - NYCD Clinics Vol. I - by Clarence Howe (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1898-99 - NYCD Clinics Vol. II (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1898-99 - Notes on Faneuil D. Weisse's Lectures on Oral Surgery by Charles Gregory Hubbell (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1899-1900 - NYCD Clinic (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1900-01 - "Styposulphide of Soda" (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1901-02 - NYCD Report of Oral Surgery Clinic by Charles Nathan (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1902-03 - NYCD Report of Oral Surgery Clinic (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1904-05 - NYCD Oral Surgery Clinic Records by Harry Mattiau (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1907-08 - NYCD Clinics (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1908-09 - NYCD Record of Oral Surgery Clinic - by Adolph Berger (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1910-11 - NYCD Report of Oral Surgery Clinics (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1911 - Inshallah Malaish (God willing - who knows!) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1911-12 - NYCD Records of Oral Surgery Clinic (Box 4, Folder 2)